<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>The blog of </title>
 <link href="http://harvardea.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://harvardea.org"/>
 <updated>2015-08-19T17:52:05-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://harvardea.org</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>States and Rights</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/14/acemoglu/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/14/acemoglu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Professor Acemoglu will discuss why it has been difficult throughout history to build state capacity, and why the development of the notion of generalized rights has been instrumental in the emergence of states that have the capacity to deliver services, but are constrained in their ability to dominate society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daron Acemoglu is the Killian Professor of Economics at MIT. In 2005 he received the John Bates Clark Medal awarded to economists under forty judged to have made the most significant contribution to economic thought and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event is open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Explore Earning-To-Give: OCS Career Panel</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/13/ocs/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/13/ocs</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in 
Consulting/Tech/Finance/Entrepreneurship?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… do you also want to make a difference outside your career for altruistic causes you care about, be it global health, animal rights or existential risks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to the career panel on earning-to-give—an international movement of people who donate money and efficiently allocate it to maximize their positive impact in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on earning-to-give: (http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/05/31/join-wall-street-save-the-world/)[http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/05/31/join-wall-street-save-the-world/]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panelists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Jeff Kaufman is a Programmer at Google, working on open source software. Along with his wife, Julia Wise, he donates half his income to the organizations most effectively working to improve the world. www.jefftk.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Ben Lawent graduated from the University of Wisconsin in 2006 and has worked as an actuary for the past eight years. He currently works on life insurance product management at John Hancock. He initially became interested in effective altruism and earning-to-give through Peter Singer’s book The Life You Can Save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Eric Gastfriend managed business and software development at Happy Cloud, a VC-backed cloud gaming tech startup, as VP and GM for three years. Eric graduated from Brown University with a degree in International Relations in 2010, and is currently in the Harvard Business School MBA Class of 2015. He is the President of Harvard University Effective Altruism, a Harvard-wide group for graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-sponsored by: Harvard College Effective Altruism (HCEA) and Harvard University Effective Altruism (HUEA)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Most Good You Can Do How Effective Altruism is Changing Ideas About Living Ethically</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/12/singer/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/12/singer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism is built upon the simple but profound idea that living a fully ethical life involves doing the “most good you can do.” Such a life requires an unsentimental view of charitable giving: to be a worthy recipient of our support, an organization must be able to demonstrate that it will do more good with our money or our time than other options open to us. Singer shows how restructuring one’s life to live altruistically often leads to greater personal fulfillment than living for oneself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event is part of Harvard Effective Altruism Week!
Find out more at: (http://harvardeaweek.org/)[http://harvardeaweek.org/]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open to the public. 
Book sales will be available through Harvard Bookstore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;——————————————————————————&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Singer is often described as the world’s most influential living philosopher. His 40 books have appeared in more than 25 languages. Singer is the Ira W. DeCamp Professor of Bioethics, Princeton University, and Laureate Professor, School of Historical and Philosophical Studies, University of Melbourne. Singer is also the founder of The Life You Can Save, an effective altruism group that encourages people to donate money to the most effective charities working today.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Elie Hassenfeld on GiveWell&#58; Measuring "Good"</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/06/hassenfeld/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2015/04/06/hassenfeld</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Elie Hassenfeld, co-founder and co-Executive Director of GiveWell, will discuss:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—How and why did GiveWell start?
—What are GiveWell’s and the Open Philanthropy Project’s plans for the future? Where do they hope to be in 1 year? 5 years?
—What is GiveWell’s role within the Effective Altruism movement as a whole?
—What are GiveWell and the Open Philanthropy Project currently working on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;——————————————————————————
Effective altruism is a new movement focused on the deceptively simple idea that we should try to do as much good as we can, as effectively as we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveWell is a non-profit dedicated to finding outstanding giving opportunities and publishing the full details of its analysis to help donors decide where to give. Peter Singer wrote of their work,”GiveWell has filled a huge gap, and at the same time has started a major trend towards transparency and demonstrated cost-effectiveness in the charitable world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event is open to the public. Come hear updates on GiveWell’s work and ask any questions you may have, both practical and philosophical.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Future of Life with AI, Nuclear Weapons, and Other Powerful Technologies</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2015/03/31/tegmark/"/>
   <updated>2015-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2015/03/31/tegmark</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Future of Life with AI, Nuclear Weapons, and Other Powerful Technologies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Max Tegmark will explore how we humans have repeatedly underestimated not only the size of our cosmos (and hence our future opportunities), but also the power of our humans minds to understand it and develop technologies with the power to enrich or extinguish humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as “Mad Max” for his unorthodox ideas and passion for adventure, Max Tegmark’s scientific interests range from precision cosmology to the ultimate nature of reality, all explored in his new popular book “Our Mathematical Universe.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is an MIT physics professor with more than two hundred technical papers and has featured in dozens of science documentaries. His work with the SDSS collaboration on galaxy clustering shared the first prize in Science magazine’s “Breakthrough of the Year: 2003.” He is also the president of the Future of Life Institute, which is launching a major research program supported by Elon Musk aimed at keeping artificial intelligence beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5pm, Tuesday, March 31
Emerson 210&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pitch Your PhD&#58; Research at the Intersection of Effectiveness and Altruism</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2015/03/26/PhD/"/>
   <updated>2015-03-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2015/03/26/PhD</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Find out what it’s like to pursue a path of changing the world through academia and get a chance to meet people who are doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young scholars from various departments and graduate schools at Harvard will pitch their research on the intersection of effectiveness and altruism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topics include:
- How to make people behave more altruistically
- What programs are most cost-effective
- Theories that allow us to say what works and what doesn’t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event will start with short presentations from the speakers, followed by break-out sessions according to interest area. This event is open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Erez Yoeli, Visiting Scholar
—Oliver Hauser, PhD Candidate
—Moshe Hoffman, Research Scientist
Harvard University Program for Evolutionary Dynamics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Promoting Effective Altruism”: If you want people to focus on effectiveness, it’s not enough to just tell them about effectiveness–you must make effectiveness public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Anders Huitfeldt
ScD Candidate, Department of Epidemiology
Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Correlation, Causation and Counterfactual Theory”: The epistemology of medical decision making, and how modern methods for causal inference can be used to learn about the safety and effectiveness of pharmaceuticals and other medical interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Guilherme Lichand
PhD candidate in Political Economy and Government&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Evidence-based policy design”: From rainfall insurance to protect poor farmers from droughts, to random audits to prevent bureaucrats from embezzling federal transfers that support municipal health spending, in my work I show that it is often the case that such policies have unintended consequences, and that rigorously documenting their effects could better inform policy design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Mauricio Fernandez Duque
PhD candidate in Political Economy and Government&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Helping those that can’t get by or those who live close by?”: I conducted a large scale field experiment in Mexico that shows the conditions in which supermarket customers contribute more to beneficiaries in their region, and how this bias is affected by an appeal to nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Apply for the Spring 2015 Philanthropy Fellowship!</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2015/01/26/apply/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2015/01/26/apply</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Harvard College Effective Altruism is proud to announce the fourth semester of our Philanthropy Fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism is the idea that we should apply evidence and reason to find the most effective ways to improve the world. HCEA Philanthropy Fellows get to attend talks and private dinners about effective altruism with well-known academics, nonprofit leaders and philanthropists. Last semester’s guests included Steven Pinker and George Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll also have discussions and social events, and do some effective and altruistic projects of our own! At the end of the semester, we’ll pick a cause that we think is important and raise funds for it ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time commitment is usually one event per week – dinner plus a talk when we’re hosting a speaker, or dinner and discussion among ourselves. There are other optional talks and social events throughout the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply, just fill out the short form below by 11:59 PM on February 2nd. Thanks for applying! We hope you’ll enjoy the chance to meet all our speakers and practice effective altruism yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/11XII6SQYeL3W6M-eWLtczravfGmYYqtwzz9bzif2_Qw/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;1200&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How much attention does climate change warrant?</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/12/04/keith-interview/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/12/04/keith-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;center&gt;&lt;t2&gt;How much attention does climate change warrant? A Conversation with Climate Scientist and Energy Technology and Public Policy Expert David Keith&lt;/t2&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Keith is Professor of Applied Physics in the School of Engineering and Applied Sciences and Professor of Public Policy at the Harvard Kennedy School. His academic work currently focuses on solar geoengineering: assessments of the technology, public engagement with its social consequences, and the development of related public policies and governance mechanisms. Following years of research on direct air capture, Keith founded and currently serves as president of Carbon Engineering, a Calgary-based start-up that works on capturing carbon dioxide from ambient air to produce low carbon fuels for transportation on an industrial scale. Keith also co-manages the Fund for Innovative Climate and Energy Research, a multimillion-dollar philanthropic geoengineering research fund established by Microsoft founder Bill Gates. Keith was named Canadian Geographic’s Environmental Scientist of the Year in 2006 and one of TIME magazine’s Heroes of the Environment in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://harvardea.org/assets/img/2014-12-04/keith.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: How much effort should we devote to combatting climate change in relation to more immediate issues like infectious diseases?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: If all you care about is direct measurable human welfare, measured by how long people are going to live or whether or not they can get enough basic materials, then I think climate change is not as high priority as pollution and other social problems we face. I think climate is an environmental problem, so for lots of reasons I would like to leave more of the natural world to be enjoyed by my great grand kids and everybody else’s. I think there is some real value to not egregiously messing with this wondrous thing that we’ve inherited, but I don’t think it’s because we need it that much. Some people want to say that the reason we should protect the climate is purely for utilitarian practical reasons: we have to do it because otherwise there is an existential threat. I don’t see much evidence for that from climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: Won’t climate change result in severe consequences for humanity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: Severe compared to what, for whom, and at what time scale? Humans are moving extraordinarily fast and causing extraordinary impact on human welfare. I worked on climate change for half of my life myself; I care about it. I just think that claims that you could compare it directly with some other threads are overblown. Take sea-level rise as an example: a two meter rise, which is a very high-end estimate, actually will occur really slowly compared to other social factors. Yes that means Miami won’t be there, but big deal. People don’t think through how big the other changes are going to be in the next two centuries. In terms of direct impact on human welfare, I would think that changes due to Southern Florida going gradually under sea level over a hundred years won’t kill anybody directly, and real estate values really aren’t meaningfully valued on that time scale. I personally think that it’s an outrageous idea that we would let the world be damaged that much, but I don’t think that the reason is the standard economist rationalization for why we should act on climate change: add up all the damages from sea level rise and whatnot and the cost of control, with discounting over time, and calculate the optimum. Under that story people like me care about climate change because we are going to make our grand kids one or two percent richer because the amount that we save from climate damages is larger than the cost to cut emissions. I find that utterly unconvincing. If the answer were the opposite, if I were to make people one percent poorer to deal with climate change, I would still want to do it for reasons that aren’t captured by economic calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: Could you comment on the general state of climate policy today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: The general state of climate policy is that it’s not going very far. Nothing much is happening. But things might happen. I’ve been involved with this for over a quarter of a century and people always think that things are going to happen and I don’t expect anything dramatic to happen, to say Paris, next year. I think that there will be announcements that make it sound good, but I’m skeptical that something really dramatic will happen. I think the underlying reasons why it’s hard to get a deal are deep, and they are not to do with opposition by this or that ugly fossil fuel company. This is not to say there isn’t that opposition, there absolute is and it’s awful, but it’s to do with the fact that the costs of cutting emissions are paid for locally while the benefits are felt a hundred years in the future. It’s the time and space aspect. We’ve dealt with externalities: in the developed world we have done an extraordinary job in improving air quality, improving water quality, toxin, DDT, and we’ve dealt with externalities that were one or two percent of GDP. China now is facing externalities from air pollution of several percent of GDP and China will very certainly deal with those &lt;b&gt;because&lt;/b&gt; if the Chinese government imposes these big costs the generation that pays the cost of emission controls will see their air get cleaner and there is a basic political deal there. But climate isn’t like that because of the very very long time delays and the global aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: Is solar geoengineering a suitable backup plan if policy changes fail us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: Solar geo-engineering seems to act quickly and, from current evidence, has pretty widespread benefits, making it likely that politicians will ultimately do it, and it doesn’t require a global agreement that cutting emissions does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the end you have to bring the emissions to zero to stabilize climate. No amount of solar engineering can solve that problem. If you don’t restrain emissions you don’t have a stable climate. And I’m just making an observation that I think politicians should react. I didn’t say anything about what I think the right answer was and I have no idea what promising means in this context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: You have conducted research on whether patents on solar geoengineering technologies could be banned and advocated for keeping these technologies in the public domain. What are the dangers of privatizing solar geoengineering?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: With incredibly technologies like this you could destroy the world. You don’t want private enterprise making nuclear weapons, and you don’t want that with geo-engineering. The decisions could impact the whole world and need to be taken as legitimately and as transparently as possible and that’s not what companies do. For these public policy matters, it’s important to discourage private enterprise and business involvement in solar geo-engineering because it has such potentially high leverage and therefore presents such a threat. The incentive to distort the facts about it would be so large so I’m strongly against doing that in a for profit mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: Where should people put their money to see environmental change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: To me I’m less excited by the big environmental NGOs, which seem a bit too business like and too captured inside the old way, so I’m more excited by some of the new ideas of how to mobilize people that are like 350.org, and the divestment movement, but there’s a whole lot of things. Personally when I give money, I give money to lobbying organizations that will change laws because I think the way we are going to restrain carbon emissions is through changing people’s attitudes and laws and I don’t think it’s through encouraging behavior that would lower individual carbon footprints because we need to bring emissions to zero and people are not going to bring their consumption to zero; you are going to do that through technological change: switching to more efficient vehicles, solar power, nuclear power what have you. So I think it’s very important to have non-governmental organizations and environmental groups fight to have these regulations passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: What are some of the most effective ways of changing the mindset of politicians and the population regarding climate change and the actions we should take?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith: These things depend on social movements! I’m really excited by the students here who are are involved with the divestment movement. I think divestment narrowly draws, if nothing else, changes, and of course the critics are right in that it won’t do much but the point of the divestment movement is trying to be really clear about what the long term consequences of our choices are with regard to carbon and what the impact of that is and to try and hold senior decision makers including the big investors and senior people who run Harvard accountable for that, and I think it’s fantastic. I think it’s part of an attempt to make a social movement that spreads more broadly the idea that people really have to demand to change, to restrain the amount of carbon emissions. I think these things are absolutely and inherently political and should not be decided in some cold analytic way. Indeed a lot of last decade’s policies been done too much by professionals who suppose they could calculate their way into the right answer and we need more activism.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Past, Present, and Future of Violence</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/11/17/pinker/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/11/17/pinker</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The past: Contrary to the popular impression view that we are living in extraordinarily violent times, rates of violence at all scales have been in decline over the course of history. The present: Human nature comprises faculties that encourage violence, such as dominance and revenge, but also faculties that inhibit it, such as self-control, empathy, and reason. The level of violence in a given society depends on how its norms and institutions affect the balance between them. The future: Prof. Pinker will speculate on which of the historical changes that reduced violence in the past will continue into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Discussion of Utility, Fairness, and Risk with Medical Ethicist Nir Eyal</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/11/14/eyal-interview/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/11/14/eyal-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://static.hwpi.harvard.edu/files/styles/profile_full/public/neyal_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nir Eyal is Associate Professor of Global Health and Social Medicine in the Center for Bioethics at Harvard Medical School and at the Department of Global Health and Population at the Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health. He is co-editor of the Oxford University Press series Population-Level Bioethics, and (among other things) chairs the Committee on Philosophy and Medicine of the American Philosophical Association. Eyal’s writings fall primarily in clinical, research, and population-level bioethics. He wrote on ethical questions surrounding HIV research, health worker shortages, healthcare rationing in resource-poor settings, informed consent, personal responsibility for health, fair risk distribution, and accrediting corporations for improving global health. Beyond bioethics, he researches egalitarian theory and consequentialism. Eyal also serves as the faculty advisor of Harvard College Effective Altruism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: How do we define ‘effectiveness’? What is the relationship between ‘effectiveness’ and ‘fairness’ and how do we balance these two considerations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: In my view, fairness matters, and it matters independently of effectiveness understood as maximizing utility. I am a philosophical egalitarian. An egalitarian means someone who cares at least some for equality. For example if we can improve the utility or the health of people who are worse off, say with very bad lifetime health or income, and improve by the same amount the utility or the health of people who are very healthy or wealthy, in my view helping those who are worse off is preferable. One reason is simply that they are worse off. Some effective altruists don’t share my position, but for our purposes this disagreement is not very important, for two reasons. One is that money and other fungible resources have decreasing marginal value, so a poor person typically benefits more from an extra dollar than Bill Gates does. Another reason why there often is agreement between utilitarians who don’t value equality intrinsically and people like me who do is that the most effective things one could do to improve wellbeing happen to address the problems of some of the world’s poorest populations. As Toby Ord emphasizes, a band of interventions such as child vaccinations and mosquito nets have cost effectiveness that far surpasses that of most other interventions currently promoted, by an order of one thousand or more. Even if you give some independent weight to equality, surely you are not going to give it the kind of weight that could override that kind of advantage in cost effectiveness. So in practice we can work very well together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another lesson from this. which I don’t think people understand enough, is that you do not need to be a utilitarian in order to be a serious effective altruist. As I said, I’m not a utilitarian. A lot of Harvard philosophers are anti-consequentialist; they think that there are some methods for promoting good consequences that remain wrong. For example, to promote good causes by torturing innocents or by lying to people can remain wrong. But they can all be effective altruists because the “band” of interventions we just talked about are of the sort that any sane person would promote when there no gross violation is demanded. It’s very rare for promoting these causes to require gross violations of individual rights or to be grossly opposed to equality. In short, every reasonable person could be and should be an effective altruist. Even if you give some weight to non-consequentialist considerations, it’s rare to find an ethicist who would just leave on the sidewalk a check for a thousand times more impact, in the name of avoiding a minor transgression or accomplishing any improvement in equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: How do we determine utility in dimensions beyond mortality or quality of living? For example how do we quantify the value of saving a child’s life versus making a blind person see again? Is valuation subjective in the sense that we care more about causes that we are connected to through experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: Health economists and epidemiologists already have techniques to try to assess overall impact. They are already in the business of comparing the prevention of mortality and that of blindness, for example. These techniques sometimes involve surveying a large population regarding which of two health states they would prefer, say a small likelihood of dying and a high likelihood of a certain degree of blindness, and then doing careful epidemiological work to glean a general lesson about the weights that should be assigned to the different states. There are many problems with the prevailing techniques for doing that. Experts are working on improving these techniques, but the bottom line is that we are already [ assigning weights to different health states ], so effective altruists could potentially use existing strategies or hone them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: Do organizations like GiveWell evaluate effectiveness only based on how effective they are at achieving their goals or also on how important their goals are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: The latter. GiveWell try to find how much impact on well being different organizations have. That’s very fortunate because it’s very easy to be effective at achieving one’s goals — all one needs to do is to find an easy goal to meet even if that goal has no importance whatsoever, or other organizations have already achieved it. GiveWell use findings from research groups such as the Disease Control Priorities second iteration, called DCP2, which gave rough numbers on the cost-effectiveness of various health interventions in developing countries. For instance, what’s more effective for combatting Cholera: giving vaccinations or teaching nurses to wash their hands? Colleagues at Harvard are promoting Cholera vaccination, but DCP2 quotes the effectiveness of teaching nurses to wash their hands at 1000 times greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: How should investing in novel, research-based solutions be balanced against tackling current, low-hanging-fruit issues using known solutions? It seems that a lot of global development work does not emphasize scientific innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: Delivering now something that’s known to work versus delivering later what is currently only experimental, if and when it gets proven, involves two differences. One is in the level of “gambling” and the other one is between close in time and farther along in time. I think there is no intrinsic value in being risk averse and in showing value in the nearer future [ as opposed to in the later future ]. But the answer will differ according to the details and the numbers in concrete cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: When making explicit models for quantifying the value of causes, should we always embed complications like risk aversion and time value of money calculations (as captured in most economic models)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: You are right in that these are issues of ethical complexity here. A related, third topic of ethical complexity: how to count deaths at different stages of life? Should we count the death of a one day old baby expected otherwise to live many years as a far worse tragedy than the death of a college student expected to live a few less years forthwith? This requires careful consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: Will we ever agree on one answer for these questions? Or perhaps we’ll have to live with uncertainty?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: One possible policy is to prioritize the areas where genuine uncertainty shows up less, so that we are relatively immune from uncertainty. By “uncertainty,” I don’t mean a matter of actual public debate. Many public debates are due to simple misunderstanding, or money infusion into the political debate. I mean genuine, deep doubt among highly informed people. One reason why I’m excited about working in global health is that there is very little doubt about the urgency of the basic causes being served—promoting the health of relatively unhealthy and poor people. Little if any uncertainty about the value of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: What are some difficult open questions related to global health?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: One hard question is how to allocate organs for transplantation. You could prioritize the patients who are likely to benefit the most from the organs, that is, those whose prospects would improve the most from receiving them. You could alternatively prioritize those patients who have been registered on the waitlist or on dialysis the longest time, which is how in the US kidneys are currently being allocated. You could also prioritize patients by how ill they would be without receiving the organ, that is, give the organs to severely ill patients. Ethicists try to find good arguments for and against different distributive principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEA: How do cultural considerations factor in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyal: Culture enters the picture, because it affects what intervention would work and which would fail. Furthermore, if for cultural reasons people feel utterly violated by an intervention that would improve their health, that’s not a happy scenario. Effective altruists should take that into account even if, like myself, they are not cultural relativists.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Elie Hassenfeld on GiveWell</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/10/30/hassenfeld-video/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/10/30/hassenfeld-video</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/LI14BTbB2fo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Nick Bostrom on Superintelligence</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/10/30/bostrom-video/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/10/30/bostrom-video</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/2YOAvkMYq64&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Against Malaria Foundation</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/10/27/mather/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/10/27/mather</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rob Mather founded the Against Malaria Foundation in 2004, which donates Long-Lasting Insecticidal Bednets to populatoins at risk of Malaria, averaging a cost of $5/net.  It was GiveWell’s top rated charity for two years.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Risks of Biotechnology</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/10/20/church/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/10/20/church</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Genetic manipulations can reintroduce extinct viruses or create new ones much deadlier than ever before. What are the dangers assoiciated with biotechnology? Can a mistake in a lab lead to a global pandemic? Can this technology be used by terrorists? What would be the implications? Is humanity doing enough to avoid these threats?
The world’s leading expert on synthetic biology and security will share his insights on these issues.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GiveWell</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/10/13/hassenfeld/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/10/13/hassenfeld</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Elie Hassenfeld graduated from Columbia in 2004 and co-founded GiveWell in mid-2007 where he currently serves as co-Executive Director. GiveWell finds outstanding charity and publishes the full details of its analysis to help donors decide where to give. The Boston Globe has called GiveWell “the gold standard for giving” and its research has attracted attention from Peter Singer and other media. GiveWell has tracked over $10 million in donations to its recommendations as a direct result of its research.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How can individuals reduce world poverty?</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/09/10/kremer/"/>
   <updated>2014-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/09/10/kremer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;​Professor Kremer will discuss how individuals can effectively help respond to world poverty—with their money and with their careers. Part of the talk will address the cost effectiveness of different ways to use financial resources, and another will present options for individuals interested in careers and international development. Q&amp;amp;A to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact HCEA at harvardea@gmail.com. Funded by the UC.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Superintelligence -- Paths, Dangers, Strategies</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/09/04/bostrom/"/>
   <updated>2014-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/09/04/bostrom</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What happens when machines surpass humans in general intelligence? Will artificial agents save or destroy us? In his new book - Superintelligence: Paths, Dangers, Strategies - Professor Bostrom explores these questions, laying the foundation for understanding the future of humanity and intelligent life. Q&amp;amp;A will follow the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funded by the U.C.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Apply for the Fall 2014 Philanthropy Fellowship!</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/09/03/apply/"/>
   <updated>2014-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/09/03/apply</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Harvard College Effective Altruism is proud to announce the third semester of our Philanthropy Fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism is the idea that we should apply evidence and reason to find the most effective ways to improve the world. HCEA Philanthropy Fellows get to attend talks and private dinners about effective altruism with well-known academics, nonprofit leaders and philanthropists. Last year’s guests included Princeton philosopher Peter Singer and Skype co-founder Jaan Tallinn. This semester, we have another exciting set, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;George Church, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arep.med.harvard.edu/gmc/&quot;&gt;Professor of Genetics at Harvard Medical School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steven Pinker, experimental psychologist, cognitive scientist, and author of &lt;a href=&quot;http://stevenpinker.com/publications/better-angels-our-nature&quot;&gt;The Better Angels of Our Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rob Mather, founder and CEO of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.againstmalaria.com/&quot;&gt;Against Malaria Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Julia Galef, cofounder and president of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rationality.org/&quot;&gt;Center for Applied Rationality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jeff Kaufman and Julia Wise, local effective altruists who donate about 50% of their income to effective charities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll also have discussions and social events, and do some effective and altruistic projects of our own! At the end of the semester, we’ll pick a cause that we think is important and raise funds for it ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time commitment is usually one event per week – dinner plus a talk when we’re hosting a speaker, or dinner and discussion among ourselves. There are other optional talks and social events throughout the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply, just fill out the short form below by 11:59 PM on September 14th. Thanks for applying! We hope you’ll enjoy the chance to meet all our speakers and practice effective altruism yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1cbSOr-ELOJcn2p5IBz47OENEmECq8fnLmkQm3fbTFzU/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;1200&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Interview with Phil Buchanan, the President of the Center for Effective Philanthropy</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/08/31/cep/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/08/31/cep</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Center for Effective Philanthropy (CEP), with a local office in Cambridge, MA and another in San Francisco, CA, is a nonprofit organization dedicated to increasing the effectiveness of philanthropic institutions. CEP operates with a four-pronged approach, developing and providing performance assessment tools, advisory services, research, and programming, to help foundation leaders maximize their effectiveness, defined as having clear goals, coherent strategies, disciplined implementation, and relevant performance indicators. Since 2001, CEP has published over 25 research reports and its assessment tools have been used by over 300 foundations worldwide, counting amongst its clientele the Ford and Bill and Melinda Gates Foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following interview conducted over phone, CEP President Phil Buchanan shares his insights on the different resources that CEP offers, the difficulties that CEP has overcome to attain its current success, and how CEP’s mission has evolved beyond providing comparative performance data to foundations to actively helping funders enhance their effectiveness and philanthropic impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin:10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2014-08-31/buchanan.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; font-style:italic;&quot;&gt;Phil Buchanan, president of Center for Effective Philanthropy&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: You have been with CEP from its inception, as its first chief executive. What was it like starting the organization from the grassroots?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: Early on it was unclear whether there would be much appreciation for what we were doing. But we recognized there were a lot of foundation leaders who felt uncomfortable by the degree to which they were isolated from critical feedback and we did a lot of things to create feedback loops where they didn’t exist. We also recognized that there was a lot of frustration with the lack of resources for thinking about what strategy means in a philanthropic context. There is a tendency to assume business frameworks will apply in philanthropy – and sometimes they do but often they do not. The work of foundations and nonprofits is different from the work of for-profits and businesses; philanthropies work on problems that defy governmental and market solutions and tend to be the toughest and most intractable problems. So we thought we could play a role in developing resources that help foundation leaders chart their course in this difficult environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: The cornerstone of these resources has been your assessment tools, which score foundations based on grantee, donor, or staff perception ratings of their effectiveness and compare foundations relative to each other. Why did you choose to use a survey-based evaluation system rather than rely on quantitative metrics such as “cost per life saved” (CPLS), as used by charity evaluators like Givewell?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: Foundations typically make grants across multiple problem areas with different goals. There is not a universal measure you can use across programs. There is no easy analog to ROI in the business context. For instance, CPLS would make sense if the program is on a disease in sub-Saharan Africa but a different metric would be needed if the focus were climate change. We think assessment approaches will vary depending on the programmatic goals and strategies. Foundations need to draw on a range of different data to inform their efforts to assess and improve. What CEP does is just one component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: What type of foundations do you serve?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: Our audience is large, staffed community and private foundations that grant at least a few million dollars a year. Eight of the ten largest grant-making institutions in the United States, and over half of the largest 50, have worked with CEP. The bulk of our clients are US foundations although we have increased the number of international foundations we serve in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: When foundations find out that they are not as effective as they thought, how do they typically respond?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: Most people who work in leadership roles in foundations do so because they really care about philanthropy, and the issues they are working on, and they want to do a good job. When they find out that their foundation perhaps does not perform as well as hoped they typically want to find out how to do better, so many foundations respond very constructively to what they learn. That is why we see improvements in foundations that assess themselves over time. Of course, as in any situation, when you provide information that conflicts with people’s beliefs you sometimes get real defensiveness. But in the majority of cases we see that people want to use the information productively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**HEA: Do you have evidence that use of your assessment tools has led to gains in effectiveness? **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: From years and years of third party surveys, we know that foundation leader overwhelmingly self-report that these tools led to change. Also, we can analyze changes in grantee perception for foundations that repeat grantee surveys and we have seen meaningful improvement on dimensions like ‘foundation’s positive impact on grantee organization’. We cannot definitively prove causality but we certainty seem to have some evidence that our assessments lead to changes and that these changes are experienced as positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: In addition to providing assessment tools, CEP does research on foundation effectiveness. What are some of CEP’s most significant findings?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: One of the more sobering findings that we see repeatedly on a variety of different topics is that there is a disconnect between foundation CEOs’ perceptions of what and how they’re doing and the perceptions of nonprofits funded by these foundations. For example, foundation leaders overwhelmingly say that nonprofits should be held to higher standards of evidence, that foundations should help them achieve these standards, and that foundations are providing that support. But the majority of grantees are receiving no such support. In other words, foundation CEOs believe that they are helping nonprofits improve their performance assessment capacity but that is not what the grantees are experiencing. There are exceptions of course – foundations that are absolutely delivering on what they say they do – but, in aggregate, there are some important disconnects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: What challenges has CEP faced?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: Early on, people didn’t know who we were and why they should listen to us. Indeed they had no good reason to listen to us! Whenever you’re doing something new, developing credibility and trust takes time. Another challenge has been recognizing that providing information that tells you how you are doing is the easy part – the hard part is knowing what to do about it. What we really want to see is improved effectiveness that translates to greater impact. It is not enough to tell people about the parts of their organization that are not working. We have to provide support and resources to help people make changes and connect people to others with similar challenges so that they can learn from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: To this end, CEP offers customized advisory services to help foundations improve their effectiveness. Could you elaborate on this process works?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: It was only in the last year or so that we’ve begun to offer these services. Previously our work was primarily diagnostic and rooted in research and assessment tools. An example of the tailored advising and consulting work we now do is when we worked with the board and CEO of a two-billion dollar in assets regionally-focused foundation where there was a sense of concern that greater impact could be achieved through greater focus but uncertainty about how to get there. We worked with the leadership and board to start them down a path toward greater focus and, we hope, greater impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example involves a billion-and-a-half dollar regionally-focused foundation that had a lot of data on how they were doing including programmatic indicators and elements of organizational effectiveness. We are helping them boil the data down into a scorecard they can share with the board to inform an annual discussion about performance and improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA: What are CEP’s plans for the near future?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchanan: Our big goal is to help foundations be more effective. The launching of our advisory services was a big part of that. We also know we need to do more to bring leaders together – to learn from each other and support each other. And there is a lot more we can and will be doing in terms of what types of data we develop and the research we execute to inform foundation leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This interview has been condensed and edited by Melody Guan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>HEA's spring 2014 research</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/06/13/research/"/>
   <updated>2014-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/06/13/research</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This semester, our fellowship did some research - in order to measure which presentations of charities attract the most interest to effective altruism. More specifically, we held giving games in Annenberg dining hall, where we gave students a dollar to donate to one of three charities. After they had donated, we asked them to sign up for our email list and that of The Life You Can Save. We presented different types of charities and presented charities with and without effectiveness information, and we measured the effect on email signups. Our main finding was that global poverty charities yielded a greater number of email signups than did more speculative charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;procedure&quot;&gt;Procedure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set up next to the exit of Annenberg dining hall and asked exiting students (mostly Harvard freshmen) to donate a dollar, which we provided, to charity. They did this by filling out an online form on one of our laptops, which presented them with three charities and prompted them to choose one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had three different sets of charities, of which we randomly selected one for each subject. The control set - Against Malaria Foundation, Schistosomiasis Control Initiative, and GiveDirectly - contains interventions in global health and poverty, described by a few bullet points that did not mention cost-effectiveness. The “effectiveness” set consists of the same charities, with descriptions extended by one bullet point to comment on the charity’s cost-effectiveness; for example, “According to GiveWell, a third-party evaluator, distributing deworming medicine to one child costs $0.73-0.99, with SCI paying about 70% of these costs.” Finally, the “speculative” set - Against Malaria Foundation, Machine Intelligence Research Institute, and 80,000 Hours - contains one option in global poverty, one in in existential risk, and one in meta-EA; described without mentioning cost-effectiveness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After choosing a charity, the subject returned the laptop and was asked by the experimenter (an HEA member) why they chose what they did. The experimenter then briefly described HEA and asked whether the subject would like to sign up for our email list or that of The Life You Can Save. We measured the number of signups for each list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data&quot;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Control&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Effectiveness&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Speculative&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total subjects&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;HEA email signups&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;TLYCS email signups&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In informal terms, we found that 62.1% of subjects signed up for HEA’s email list in the control group, compared to 47.5% in the cost-effectiveness group, and only 41.9% in the group with more speculative charities. The difference between the control and speculative groups was strong enough that the result is statistically significant. The results were qualitatively similarly (but with fewer overall signups) for TLYCS’s email list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used two-tailed Fisher’s exact tests, which give the following p-values and relative risks. (A relative risk of 0.5 means that the intervention group is half as likely to show the effect as controls.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; (Fisher’s exact)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Relative risk (95% CI)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Speculative, HEA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;0.03&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.68 (0.47-0.96)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Effectiveness, HEA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.75 (0.52-1.07)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Speculative, TLYCS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.07&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.67 (0.42-1.06)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Effectiveness, TLYCS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.32&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.80 (0.53-1.23)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting Harvard students with more traditional, global poverty charities appears to generate more interest in effective altruism than does presenting them with charities in existential risk and meta-EA. In our case, we received significantly more email signups when presenting global poverty charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to draw conclusions with respect to the inclusion of cost-effectiveness information. We don’t know whether the decrease in signups resulted from having cost-effectiveness information or from the blurbs just taking longer to read; this was a flaw in the design of our experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time we do giving games to generate interest in EA, we’ll keep these results in mind! Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Aversion Factoring and Career Choice</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/17/critch/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/17/critch</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We often limit ourselves by avoiding things we find bothersome or scary.  But for almost anything you find bothersome, there’s someone out there who doesn’t!  How does that work?  Can you copy their enjoyment-powers?  If so, you have many more options for growth, career choice, and general do-gooding.  This presentation is based around a technique taught at the Center for Applied Rationality for using aversions as a source of creativity, and then getting over them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critch’s interest in rationality began as a teenager growing up in Newfoundland, Canada, where he says he “just had a lot of time to think about it”. When he was 14, he made his first attempt to extrapolate his instinctive preferences into a function whose expected integral he wanted to maximize. (In college he found out that some economists had been crazy enough to think humans worked this way automatically). He also won numerous national awards in mathematics and public-speaking competitions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dinner with Toby Ord</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/16/toby/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/16/toby</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Toby Ord is a James Martin Research Fellow with the Programme on the Impacts of Future Technology, but also contributes towards the FHI’s research aims. His FHI research interests include both theoretical and practical ethics, with a focus on questions concerning the big picture. He is currently investigating the topic of moral uncertainty: the study of how to act when we are unsure of the relevant moral considerations. This is a much neglected area of theoretical ethics with many strong practical implications. He is also exploring a number of questions regarding global poverty, such as the extent of our personal responsibilities and how we should prioritise within aid spending. Finally, he has an ongoing interest in questions about future technologies and global catastrophic risks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dinner with Carl Shulman</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/09/shulman/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/09/shulman</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Carl Shulman is a Research Fellow at the Machine Intelligence Research Institute who has authored and co-authored several papers on AI risk, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“How Hard is Artificial Intelligence? Evolutionary Arguments and Selection Effects,” an analysis of the implications of the Observation selection effecton the Evolutionary argument for human-level AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Whole Brain Emulation and the Evolution of Superorganisms,” which argues for the existence of pressures favoring the emergence of increased coordination between emulated brains, in the form of superorganisms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Implications of a Software-Limited Singularity,” which argues for the high probability of a human-level IA before 2060.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, he worked at Clarium Capital Management, a global macro hedge fund, and at the law firm Reed Smith LLP. He attended New York University School of Law and holds a BA in philosophy from Harvard University.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How much can we generalize from impact evaluation results?</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/04/vivalt/"/>
   <updated>2014-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/04/04/vivalt</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s important to evaluate the impact of interventions in development, so as to inform future actions and policies. But – given that individual studies are rooted in particular contexts – when and how can we generalize their findings across settings? Dr. Vivalt will share her findings. Q&amp;amp;A to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us after the talk for a research-athon - An Introduction to Meta–Analyses. From 2 to 6 pm, Dr. Vivalt will teach participants how to do some of the work that AidGrade does. Volunteers will gain experience and contribute to AidGrade’s research!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eva Vivalt is a post-doctoral fellow at New York University. She has a Ph.D. in Economics and an M.A. in Mathematics from the University of California, Berkeley and spent two years as a Young Professional at the World Bank, where she worked in the Development Economics Research Group. Eva completed an M.Phil. in Development Studies at Oxford University on a Commonwealth Scholarship after obtaining her A.B. from Dartmouth College. She previously worked as a consultant in the World Bank’s Development Economics Research Group and has extensive experience with international development, including field experience, through work with the UN Development Program, Oxford Development Abroad, and numerous other charity groups.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Emotion, Reason, and Altruism</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/03/11/greene/"/>
   <updated>2014-03-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/03/11/greene</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why do people have radically different opinions as to who to help and how? How can we get along with people who seem to fundamentally disagree with us about what to want? Professor Josh Greene addresses this and more in &lt;em&gt;Emotion, Reason, and Altruism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joshua Greene directs Harvard’s Moral Cognition Lab, which uses techniques from cognitive neuroscience to study moral decision-making, trying to understand what causes disagreement on moral questions and how they can be resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Future of Life: a Cosmic Perspective</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2014/03/04/tegmark/"/>
   <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2014/03/04/tegmark</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Prof. Tegmark will explore how we humans have repeatedly underestimated not only the size of our cosmos (and hence our future opportunities), but also the power of our humans minds to understand it and develop technologies with the power to enrich or extinguish humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as “Mad Max” for his unorthodox ideas and passion for adventure, Max Tegmark’s scientific interests range from precision cosmology to the ultimate nature of reality, all explored in his new popular book “Our Mathematical Universe”. He is an MIT physics professor with more than two hundred technical papers and has featured in dozens of science documentaries. His work with the SDSS collaboration on galaxy clustering shared the first prize in Science magazine’s “Breakthrough of the Year: 2003.”&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Our winter 2013 fundraiser is finished!</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/02/05/fundraiser/"/>
   <updated>2014-02-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/02/05/fundraiser</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This holiday season, HEA fundraised for GiveWell’s recommended charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that fundraiser is over, we’d like to extend a warm thank you to everyone who participated - give yourself a pat on the back! The money and time you donated really will make an impact in the world, by providing money and cost-effective medical treatment to people in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final total donated through our fundraiser was &lt;strong&gt;$42,250.82&lt;/strong&gt;. Wow! We’re totally blown away by the response we received. Here’s where our donors chose to give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;287&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/2014-02-05/image00.png&quot; width=&quot;510&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our donors requested that their contributions not count towards the anonymous match, because they would have donated it anyway and the didn’t want to mess up the incentives of the match for other people. Counting just the money that would have gone elsewhere without the fundraiser, we &lt;em&gt;moved&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;$4350.41&lt;/strong&gt; to GiveWell’s top charities from other uses. These donations were matched dollar-for-dollar by our anonymous donor!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;286&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/2014-02-05/image03.png&quot; width=&quot;624&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received many small donations from Harvard students by fundraising in the Annenberg dining hall, and by reaching out to individual students. Some of our members also asked for donations as holiday gifts from family, friends, and community members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the charts below, we’ve &lt;em&gt;estimated&lt;/em&gt; the number of small, student donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;128&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/2014-02-05/image02.png&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;288&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/2014-02-05/image01.png&quot; width=&quot;575&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you once again to everyone who participated. We look forward to seeing you at our events this spring!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Apply for the Spring Philanthropy Fellowship!</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/news/2014/01/29/apply/"/>
   <updated>2014-01-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/news/2014/01/29/apply</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Harvard Effective Altruism is proud to announce the second semester of our Philanthropy Fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism is the idea that we should apply evidence and reason to find the most effective ways to improve the world. HEA Philanthropy Fellows get to attend talks and private dinners about effective altruism with well-known academics, nonprofit leaders and philanthropists. Last semester’s guests included Princeton philosopher Peter Singer and Skype co-founder Jaan Tallinn. This semester, we have another exciting set, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joshua Greene, moral psychologist and philosopher and author of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Moral-Tribes-Emotion-Reason-Between/dp/1594202605/&quot;&gt;Moral Tribes&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eva Vivalt, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aidgrade.org/&quot;&gt;AidGrade&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leah Libresco, policy researcher, rationalist and blogger;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and Jeff Kaufman and Julia Wise, local effective altruists who donate about 50% of their income to effective charities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll also have discussions ourselves, host talks by members of HEA, and do some effective and altruistic projects of our own! At the end, we’ll pick a cause that we think is important and raise funds for it ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time commitment is usually one event per week–dinner plus a talk when we’re hosting a speaker, or dinner and discussion among ourselves. There are other optional talks and social events throughout the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply, just fill out the short form below by &lt;strong&gt;February 9&lt;/strong&gt;. Thanks for applying! We hope you’ll enjoy the chance to meet all our speakers and practice effective altruism yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/11ee_JTDf2PPkmxWUDGSLL3XlfU2TrWbTiAnPrcoRHGM/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;1200&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Winter 2013 fundraiser</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/fundraisers/winter2013/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-30T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/fundraisers/fundraiser-w2013</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This holiday season, &lt;a href=&quot;http://harvardea.org/&quot;&gt;Harvard Effective Altruism&lt;/a&gt; is fundraising for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/&quot;&gt;GiveWell&lt;/a&gt;’s top-rated charities—which we think represent our &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; opportunity to do good in the world. Give back effectively this year—give with us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first $5000 of donations will be matched by an anonymous donor. And don’t wait: our fundraiser will end on January 20th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-give-now&quot;&gt;Why give now:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always a good time to give to effective charities—you can make a surprisingly large impact on someone’s life! Our fundraiser is an especially good opportunity for three reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, an anonymous donor has agreed to match our first $5000 of donations—so you can give twice as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, by spreading the word through our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/392222467547974/&quot;&gt;Facebook event&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rally.org/harvardea#feed&quot;&gt;Rally page&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XRsPVYNIUyc&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;Youtube video&lt;/a&gt;, you can convince others to donate!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we’re competing with student groups at Princeton and Rutgers to see who can fundraise the most! I know I’m still sore about our one loss this football season…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-charities&quot;&gt;Our charities:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; distributes cash to very poor individuals in Kenya and Uganda. Strong evidence indicates that cash transfers lead recipients to spend more on their basic needs (such as food) and may allow recipients to make investments with high returns, with no evidence of large increases in spending on items like alcohol or tobacco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.imperial.ac.uk/schisto&quot;&gt;Schistosomiasis Control Initiative&lt;/a&gt; (SCI)&lt;/strong&gt; supports programs that treat people for parasitic worm infections that cause short-term symptoms such as anemia, and may cause longer-term developmental problems. These worms are extremely inexpensive to treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dewormtheworld.org/&quot;&gt;Deworm the World Initiative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; also seeks to treat parasitic worm infections, but focuses more on advocacy and technical assistance to governments providing deworming and less on direct treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparative-advantages&quot;&gt;Comparative advantages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveDirectly has the most direct and robust case for impact. It also has potential to improve the aid community’s understanding of, and interest in, cash transfer programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SCI’s activities have the highest estimated cost-effectiveness; it is most likely that they have the largest impact on people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DtWI has the highest potential for &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givewell.org/2011/12/16/leverage-in-charity/&quot;&gt;leverage&lt;/a&gt; (doing extra good through indirect means), as it focuses on influencing governments spending rather than covering all costs with its own funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more in-depth information, you can visit GiveWell’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/charities/top-charities&quot;&gt;top charities page&lt;/a&gt;, or read their in-depth reviews of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/international/top-charities/give-directly&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/international/top-charities/schistosomiasis-control-initiative&quot;&gt;SCI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/international/top-charities/deworm-world-initiative&quot;&gt;DtWI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-donate&quot;&gt;How to Donate:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1&quot;&gt;Step 1:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about our charities and choose how much to give to each one. Which do you think is the most effective, and why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2&quot;&gt;Step 2:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For donations under $20, you can give right now on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://rally.org/f/bHVNxGpEqLe&quot;&gt;Rally page&lt;/a&gt;. Then email &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#118;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#097;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;&amp;#104;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#118;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#097;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&lt;/a&gt; (from the account you submit with Rally) to tell us how to split your donation between our three charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For donations over $20, we ask that you donate directly through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/charities/top-charities&quot;&gt;GiveWell’s website&lt;/a&gt;. So that we can &lt;strong&gt;match&lt;/strong&gt; your donation: after entering your personal information, check “Dedicate my donation in honor of someone” and enter “Name: Harvard Effective Altruism”, “Email Address: harvardea@gmail.com”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3&quot;&gt;Step 3:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell your friends! Help us spread the message of effective giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can join and share our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/392222467547974/&quot;&gt;Facebook event&lt;/a&gt;, like our &lt;a href=&quot;https://rally.org/harvardea&quot;&gt;Rally page&lt;/a&gt;, or watch and share our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XRsPVYNIUyc&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;Youtube video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-harvard-effective-altruism&quot;&gt;About Harvard Effective Altruism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a campus group dedicated to spreading the ideas of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_altruism%20&quot;&gt;effective altruism&lt;/a&gt;—that we should apply evidence and reason to find the most effective ways to improve the world. Read more on our &lt;a href=&quot;http://harvardea.org/&quot;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Evaluating Effective Charities</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/11/12/hassenfeld/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/11/12/hassenfeld</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How can you maximize the impact of your charitable giving? What distinguishes the most effective causes and organizations? Elie Hassenfeld, co-founder and co-Executive Director of &lt;a href=&quot;http://givewell.org/&quot;&gt;GiveWell&lt;/a&gt;, will describe how his organization is revolutionizing charity evaluation with completely transparent, rigorous analysis. Q&amp;amp;A to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elie Hassenfeld graduated from Columbia in 2004 and co-founded GiveWell in mid-2007 where he currently serves as co-Executive Director. GiveWell finds outstanding charity and publishes the full details of its analysis to help donors decide where to give. The Boston Globe has called GiveWell “the gold standard for giving” and its research has attracted attention from Peter Singer and other media. GiveWell has tracked over $10 million in donations to its recommendations as a direct result of its research.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Effective Altruism</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/11/08/singer/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/11/08/singer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism is a new movement consisting of many individuals and several independent organizations, all focused on the deceptively simple idea that we should try to do as much good as we can. The existence of this movement raises many interesting questions, both practical and philosophical, which this talk will discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Singer is the Ira W. DeCamp Professor of Bioethics at the Princeton University Center for Human Values, and Laureate Professor at the Center for Applied Philosophy and Public Ethics at the University of Melbourne.  He is well known for his philosophical work, as well as for his books–most recently including &lt;em&gt;The Life You Can Save&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Singer will also speak on “Ethics and Animals: Where Are We Now?” at 12 PM in Austin 200 (Ames Courtroom), 1515 Massachusetts Ave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This event is co-sponsored by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://petrieflom.law.harvard.edu/&quot;&gt;Petrie-Flom Center for Health Law Policy, Biotechnology, and Bioethics at Harvard Law School&lt;/a&gt;, with support from the Oswald DeN. Cammann Fund, as well as Harvard’s Departments of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~phildept/&quot;&gt;Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.harvard.edu/&quot;&gt;Economics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>So You Want to be a Technology Developer...</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/30/tallinn/"/>
   <updated>2013-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/30/tallinn</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The roots of Skype go back to one email. If that email hadn’t been sent, the world today might be different. In general, technology development is not something that “just happens” – instead, it’s a result of particular actions by individual people. Moreover, the responsibility of technology developers must increase proportionally to the power of their creations. The talk sketches out a vision of what it means to be a responsible technology developer, using behind the scenes stories and videos from the early days of Skype development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jaan Tallinn is one of the programmers behind the Kazaa file sharing platform, and a founding engineer of Skype. He is also a partner in the seed-stage venture firm Ambient Sound Investments, a co-founder of the Cambridge Centre for the Study of Existential Risk, and a former member of the Estonian President’s Academic Advisory Board. He describes himself as a futurist, hacker, investor and physicist, in that order. He holds a degree in physics from the University of Tartu.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photography and Poverty</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/22/middleton/"/>
   <updated>2013-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/22/middleton</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why do so many charity photos look identical? What do Apple’s design principles, World War II propaganda, the infamous MySpace mirror portrait and mobile phone video scandals all have in common? At their root is the power that has created much of our Western visual understanding of poverty - as well as the power that will allow us to change it for the better. As major international organizations struggle with the question of how to keep poverty photography relevant - and keep the money rolling in - we can look at how the era of social networks and mobile technology will allow us to personally have a hand in crafting a new, subtle and infinitely ‘smarter’ series of visuals around poverty - a critical tool in helping to spread the idea of effective charitable giving based on a more informed understanding of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael T. Middleton has done photography on six continents and his work has appeared in gallery shows in the US and France, where his Absent Friends portrait series was an Official Selection in the 2011 Prix de la Photographie in Paris. His talk, “Poverty: Lessons Learned from Photography” has been given at universities including Princeton, Rutgers, Oxford, Cambridge and Imperial College in London.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Which careers do the most good?</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/17/macaskill/"/>
   <updated>2013-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/17/macaskill</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll spend over 80,000 hours of your life working—you should make the most of them. But if you want to make a difference, what should you do? Work for nonprofits? Try to change policy? Find a malaria vaccine? Go into finance and give it all away?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80,000 Hours founder William MacAskill will tell you about his organisation’s research into this question, and explain how it can help you find the career where you’ll have the biggest impact. You might leave with some surprising conclusions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William MacAskill is the founder of Oxford’s Centre for Effective Altruism and of &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/&quot;&gt;80,000 Hours&lt;/a&gt;, a personal advisory service on using your time to do the most good. Formerly a Fulbright scholar at Princeton University, and currently a PhD candidate at Oxford University, he has been featured on BBC News On-line, The Today Programme, NPR, CNBC and The Washington Post. Between them, his non-profits have raised over $3 million for the most cost-effective charities, with a further $130 million pledged.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Effective Charity or Mobilization for Institutional Reform?</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/09/pogge/"/>
   <updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/10/09/pogge</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Professor Pogge will discuss whether some institutional reform efforts may be as effective or more effective than “effective altruism” and also whether effectiveness is the only standard by which such alternative ways of protecting people are to be compared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Pogge is the Director of the Global Justice Program and Leitner Professor of Philosophy and International Affairs at Yale University. Additionally, he is the Research Director of the Centre for the Study of the Mind in Nature at the University of Oslo; a Professorial Research Fellow at the Centre for Applied Philosophy and Public Ethics at Charles Sturt University; and Professor of Political Philosophy at the University of Central Lancashire’s Centre for Professional Ethics. He is also an editor for social and political philosophy for the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy and a member of the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Global Poverty&#58; Why Should We Care?</title>
   <link href="http://harvardea.org/event/2013/09/12/temkin/"/>
   <updated>2013-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://harvardea.org/event/2013/09/12/temkin</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Each year, millions of children die from readily preventable causes. This raises an obvious and poignant question. What, if anything, should our reaction be to the apparent fact that each one of us could easily prevent the deaths of many innocent people who are not responsible for their unfortunate plight?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Larry Temkin is a professor of philosophy at Rutgers. He holds a Ph.D. from Princeton and is the author of “Rethinking the Good: Moral Ideals and the Nature of Practical Reasoning” (OUP, 2012) and “Inequality” (OUP, 1993). He has received fellowships from the Danforth Foundation, the National Humanities Center, Harvard’s Safra Center for Ethics, All Souls College Oxford, the National Institutes of Health, the Australian National University, and Princeton, where he was the Laurance S. Rockefeller Visiting Professor for Distinguished Teaching. He has received eight major teaching awards, including Rice University’s George R. Brown Prize for Excellence in Teaching, the Nicholas Salgo Distinguished Teacher Award, the Phi Beta Kappa Outstanding Teaching Award, and Rutgers’s Award for Distinguished Contributions to Undergraduate Education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lecture will take place in Harvard’s Science Center, Hall E (in the basement), and will be followed by a Q&amp;amp;A period.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
